Preliminary Inventory to the Toby Olson Papers, 1970-2000
Department of Special Collections
Toby Olson Papers,
1970-2000
M1296
Olson, Toby.
30 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Manuscript drafts, proofs, notes, correspondence, and publications.
Administrative Information
Access
Access restricted until processing is completed. Please check with the department.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2002
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Manuscript drafts, proofs, notes, correspondence, and publications.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Hamady, Walter.; Sorrentino, Gil.; Taggart, John.; Tarn, Nathaniel.; American literature--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Seaview, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 1)
  First and second drafts; A draft with notes; Final draft; Letter: Bernard Hoepffner, regarding French translation
- The Life of Jesus, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 1)
  First draft, with roughs and notes; Rough manuscript; Third draft; Proof
- At Sea, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 2)
  First called "Angle of Repose," then "Certain Women". Various drafts; Research materials
- Tampico and Write Letter to Billy, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 2)
  Various drafts and notes; Some false starts
- Dorit [Opera], Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 3)
  Drafts; Materials; Programs; Reviews
- Chihuahua [Opera], Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 3)
  Drafts and notes
- The Bitter Half, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 3)
- Poetry manuscripts and revisions, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 3)
- Susanna Styron movie correspondence and her screenplay, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 3)
- Gale Research autobiography correspondence, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 3)
- Dorit in Lesbos, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 4)
  First draft; Notes and research materials; Raw, early manuscript material; Second and third drafts; Proof and edited manuscript; Final manuscript; Poem copies
- Diane Wakoski: Symposium [edited by Olson], Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 4)
  Correspondence and materials; Wakoski correspondence
- The Woman Who Escaped From Shame, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 5)
  First and second drafts; Notes; Third draft; Other drafts and revisions; Some correspondence; John Taggart Correspondence
- Manuscripts from Friends, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 6)
- Review of Contemporary Fiction: Barthelme/Olson Issue, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 7)
  Correspondence and materials
- Misc. Correspondence., Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 7)
- Correspondence: Various Writers, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, Editors, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 8)
  Ellen Levine Literary Agency; New Directions; James Laughlin; Jonathan Galassi; John Glussman; Alan Peacock
- Correspondence: Various Writers and Others, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 8)
- At Sea [called Certain Women], Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 9)
- Human Nature, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 9)
- Tampico, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 9)
- At Sea, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 10)
  Edited draft
- Write Letter to Billy, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 10)
  First, second, third drafts, notes
- Unfinished Building, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 10)
  Copyedited copy
- Walter Hamady correspondence, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 11)
- Utah, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 12)
  First draft; Notes and materials; Second and third drafts; Copyedited manuscript; Last draft, with some work; Galleys
- The Bitter Half, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 13)
  Notes
- Write Letter to Billy, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 13)
  Copyedited proof; Drafts and notes
- BOOKS, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 14)
  Dorit in Lesbos; Utah; The Woman Who Escaped From Shame; Seaview; At Sea; The Life of Jesus; Write Letter to Billy; We Are the Fire; Human Nature; Unfinished Buildinq; Changing Appearance; Home; The Florence Poems; Vectors; City; The Hawk-Foot Poems; Writing Talks; Standard--4, Aviator Press [broadside]; Anima [off-print of poems]
- Magazines, Accession no. 2001-267 (Box 14)
  Center #6; Philadelphia magazine, Nov. 1986; Inquirer magazine, July, 1993; Margins [Diane Wakoski Symposium 1/2/3, 1976; New Directions #29; New Directions #35; New Directions #40; Loves, Etc.; Inside Outer Space; Boundary 2, 1980; Intrepid Anthology, 1976; The Paris Review #99; The American Experience: A Radical Reader, 1970; Contemporary American Fiction, 1983; Caterpillar #5; New Letters, 1981-82; Sumac, 1971; Handbook #111; The Falcon#4; Stations #2; Mulch #1; Occurrence #6; The Gettysburg Review, Vol.2 #1; The Painted Bride, Vol. 3 #2; The Painted Bride, Vol. 4 #1; The Painted Bride, 1975-1993; The Painted Bride #45; Sumac: An Active Anthology, 1974; Perfect Lies; The review of Contemporary Fiction [Barthelme/Olson issue]; Washington Square #6; Colorado Review #2, Fall, 1992; Colorado Review #1, 1999; Denver Quarterly, Vol. 34 #4, 2000; Conjunctions #3; Conjuctions #13; Conjunctions #28
- Miscellaneous letters -113, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 1)
- Letters:, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 1)
  Walter Hamady -38, John Taggart -15, Gil Sorrentino -17, Nathaniel Tarn -16
- Letters, Reviews, etc.: related to the following:, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 1)
  We Are the Fire and The Wrestlers and Other Poems; The Florence Poems and Unfinished Building; The Life of Jesus; Write Letter to Billy; Seaview; The Woman Who Escaped From Shame; Dorit In Lesbos; Utah; Dorit (opera)
- Other Materials, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 1)
  Grants and Fellowships; Reading Trips; Royalty Statements
- Reviews, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 2)
- PEN/Faulkner Award materials, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 2)
- Some magazine publications, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 2)
- Magazine Publications, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 3)
- Revision Pages: Writer Letter to Billy, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
- Proof: Unfinished Building, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
- Proof: "Reading", Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
- Revision pages: Human Nature, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
- Revision pages: "Seeing Duchamp" [essay], Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
- Libretto, review program: "Chihuahua", Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
- The Occidental Review, edited by Olson in Undergraduate school at Occidental, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 4)
  Two issues
- Broadsides, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 5)
  "Another Popular Song"; "Tools"; "Just This"; "from Home"; "From El Monte"; :A Very Cold Day"; "The Trumpet Vine"; "Cold House" [Perishable Press]; "Priorities" [post card]; "A Kind of Psychology" [post card]
- CD: "Birdsongs", Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 5)
- CD: "Three Songs From Home", Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 5)
- Tape: Olson Reading Home, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 5)
- Books, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 5)
  La Vida de Jesus [translation of The Life of Jesus]; Seaview [English Publication]; Seaview, U.S.A. [French translation]; Sitting in Guesvik. Black Mesa press.; Reading. Friend of Typography.; Tow Standards. Salient Seedling Press.; Still/Quiet. Landlocked Press.; Aesthetics. Membrane Press.; Pig/s Book. Dr. Generosity press.; The Wrestlers and Other Poems. Barlenmir House.
- Books: the perishable press, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 5)
  Fishing; BirdSongs; Maps; The Pool; Worms into Nails; Doctor Miriam; The Brand; Three and One
- A few magazine publications, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
- Card Catalogue of all publications: 1965-1987, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
- Dorit [chamber opera]: tape and libretto, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
- Chihuahua [chamber opera]: tape and libretto, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
- CD: Olson reading, 10-6-01, Woodland Patterns, Milwaukee, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
- TAPE: musical pieces:, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
  Reading [short story]; Facing [poem]; John Leonard NPR review of Dorit in Lesbos; NPR interview with Epstein and Olson, re. Dorit [opera]
- Photographs, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, Accession no. 2002-010 (Box 7)
  Includes important letter from Denise Levertov re her divorce
- Untitled: typescript poems,1966 - 1973, Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)
- Unfinished business: poems / by Toby Olson, ca. 1990, Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)
- We are the fire: a selection of poem, 1970 - 1984 / by Toby Olson, ca. 1984, Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)
- Untitled: typescript poems,1967 - 1985, Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)
- Untitled: typescript poems,1972 - 1973; n.d., Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)
- Untitled: typescript poems,1972 - 1985, Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)
- The sky is a big circle, and we are in the center, safe / by Toby Olson, n.d., Accession no. 2002-010; 1 typed manuscript (Box 8)